{"tossups": [{"question": "This President averted a strike by signing the Adamson Act to grant an eight-hour workday to railroad workers. This man oversaw the deportation of over 200 anarchists on the \u201cSoviet Ark,\u201d many of whom were arrested in a series of raids ordered by his attorney general, Mitchell Palmer; this President\u2019s Espionage Act, which justified those arrests, was upheld by the Supreme Court due to wartime conditions. For ten points, name this president who led the United States through World War I.", "answer": "(Thomas) Woodrow<b> Wilson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A 2003 court case ruled that Job Charnock was not the founder of this city. Lord Curzon created a monument in this city\u2019s Dalhousie Square to commemorate an incident, of which John Zephaniah Howell wrote an account of brutalities committed in Fort William by the Nawab of Bengal. 146 prisoners were locked in a cell in this city, in which only 23 survived the conditions. British prisoners were kept in the\u201cBlack Hole\u201d of, for ten points, what capital of West Bengal in eastern India?", "answer": "<b> Kolkata</b> (accept<b> Calcutta</b>; accept additional information relating to the Black Hole of <b>Calcutta</b> or<b> Kolkata</b> after \u201cCurzon\u201d is mentioned) (8) A building designed by this man, Wardenclyffe, was the focus of a 2012 preservation effort led by the webcomic<em> The Oatmeal</em>. David Bowie portrayed this real-life person in the 2006 film<em> The Prestige</em>. This man\u2019s development of a system licensed by George Westinghouse led to a vicious conflict with Thomas Edison, who championed a competing system involving direct current. For ten points, name this Serbian-American scientist and inventor who names a coil that produces AC electricity. ANSWER: Nikola<b> Tesla</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The unveiling of this structure\u2019s design led James Webb and Ross Perot to withdraw support, with Perot controversially insulting its architect as an \u201ceggroll.\u201d An opponent of this structure called it a \u201cgash of shame,\u201d as its design emulates the shape of a closed wound. Frederick Hart\u2019s<em> Three Soldiers</em> overlooks this memorial, of which visitors often create crayon rubbings. Maya Lin designed, for ten points, what memorial that lists the name of servicemen who died in a Southeast Asian War?", "answer": "<b> Vietnam Veterans Memorial</b> (accept descriptions of the<b> Vietnam</b> War<b> memorial</b>; accept descriptions of the<b> Vietnam Wall</b>) Page 2", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "Description acceptable. A speech about Verres claims that people with this status could not be harmed if they proclaimed this status. Before being placed on trial, the Apostle Paul claimed this status to a centurion. John F. Kennedy noted that \u201ctwo thousand years ago,\u201d this status was \u201cthe proudest boast\u201d before comparing it to being \u201cein Berliner.\u201d Slaves could not hold this status unless freed. Women held only a minimal form of, for ten points, what legal status in an ancient Italian empire?", "answer": "<b> Roman</b> <b>citizen</b>ship (accept descriptions of being a<b> citizen</b> <b>of</b> <b>Rome</b>; prompt on \u201ccitizen(ship)\u201d; prompt on \u201c(being) Roman,\u201d but do not prompt on \u2018intermediate\u2019 answers such as \u201cbeing a Roman male,\u201d \u201cbeing a free Roman,\u201d etc.; accept<b> civis Romanus</b> sum, and prompt on civis)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A county in this colony was sued by James Maury in the Parson\u2019s Cause, which involved a dispute between this state\u2019s established Anglican clergy and its government. The defense in that case was led by a member of this colony\u2019s legislature, the House of Burgesses, who proclaimed \u201cGive me liberty or give me death\u201d in 1775. Patrick Henry was a politician from, for ten points, what American colony, the most populous before the Revolution, where the House of Burgesses met in Jamestown and Williamsburg?", "answer": "<b> Virginia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This site includes the Torreon tower, which was once used as an observatory, and a Popular District where commoners lived. The Huatana stone and the Room of the Three Windows at this site were dedicated to a sun god, Inti. This site is situated above the Urubamba River and was constructed as an estate for Pachacuti. Hiram Bingham studied, for ten points, what \u201clost city of the Incas?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Machu Picchu</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "One of this empire\u2019s colonial holdings was a company co-founded by Carl Peters and opposed by the failed Abushiri Revolt. This empire, which seized a naval base at Tsingtao from the Chinese in 1898, sent the<em> Panther</em> gunboat to Morocco in a failed attempt to break the Entente Cordiale alliance of two of its rivals. For ten points, name this country that engaged in a naval arms race with Great Britain and signed the 1879 Dual Alliance with Austria-Hungary, an alliance that lasted until they lost World War I.", "answer": "<b> Germany</b> (or the<b> German</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "Charles Tyson Yerkes thwarted this man\u2019s efforts to build part of the London Underground through London United Tramways. This man founded New York\u2019s Metropolitan Club and orchestrated a business deal with Elbert Gary and William Henry Moore in 1901. This man created a coalition of bankers to mitigate the Panic of 1907; earlier, he allied with the Rothschilds to sell gold to replenish the US Treasury during the Panic of 1893. For ten points, name this American financier, the namesake of a bank that merged with Chase in 2000.", "answer": "John Pierpont \u201cJ.P.\u201d<b> Morgan</b>, Sr.", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In 1962\u2019s<em> Robinson v. California</em>, the Supreme Court used this amendment to strike down a California law criminalizing narcotic addiction. Modern applications of this amendment often rely on the idea of \u201cevolving standards of decency.\u201d Excessive bail is included in this amendment as an example of a prohibition found to violate \u201chuman dignity.\u201d 1972\u2019s<em> Furman v. Georgia</em> temporarily outlawed the death penalty by applying, for ten points, what Constitutional amendment that prohibits cruel and unusual punishment?", "answer": "<b> 8</b>th Amendment to the US Constitution BONUS:<em> Roper v. Simmons</em> cited the 8th Amendment while restricting the use of the death penalty for people with this characteristic. While the 26th Amendment expanded a certain right to more Americans, it did not expand that right to people with this characteristic. Description acceptable. ANSWER: being<b> younger than 18</b> years old (accept any description of being<b> young</b>, a<b> minor</b>, a <b>juvenile</b>, a<b> child</b>, etc.; accept being a<b> teen</b>ager, despite the possible ambiguity that 19 presents) Page 4", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was disguised as a drunk flight attendant to avoid suspicion on a Bristol Britannia plane. A month earlier, as this man was getting off a bus in Buenos Aires, Peter Malkin and two other agents of Mossad tackled and abducted this man. Hannah Arendt wrote about the \u201cbanality of evil\u201d as displayed by this man at his 1961 trial for war crimes in Jerusalem. For ten points, name this man who hid in Argentina for a decade before being executed for his role in orchestrating the Holocaust.", "answer": "(Otto) Adolf<b> Eichmann</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>Near the end of a novel set in this country, two men reconcile when one gives the other a sympathy wreath for his dead wife and the other donates funds to build a new church.</b> <b>In a novel set in this country, the (+)</b> <b>Smales family migrates to their servant\u2019s village;</b> <b>that novel,</b><em><b> July\u2019s People</b></em><b>, includes Nadine Gordimer\u2019s prediction of a civil war and was once banned in Gauteng Province. The social activist (*)</b> Arthur Jarvis is murdered by Absalom Kumalo in this country in Alan Paton\u2019s<em> Cry the Beloved Country</em>. For ten points, name this country, where those novels were written during the Apartheid era.", "answer": "Republic of<b> South Africa</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>Between his stints on the Supreme Court, Charles Evans Hughes served in this Cabinet position under Harding and Coolidge. In this position, Elihu Root helped design the 1901</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Platt Amendment, and another holder of this Cabinet position named John Hay</b> <b>formalized the Open Door Policy to keep trade with (*)</b> China balanced. Under Taft, a holder of this position promoted loans to countries in Latin America as part of \u201cdollar diplomacy.\u201d For ten points, name this Cabinet position that oversees foreign policy.", "answer": "<b> Secretary of State</b> (prompt on State)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>The terms of this legislation were debated by delegates from nine southern states in the Nashville Convention. By the terms of this legislation, Texas gave up claims to western lands in exchange for trading off ten million dollars of debt. In this legislation, (+) California was admitted as a free state, but the New Mexico and Utah Territories were established under (*) </b> popular sovereignty. For ten points, name this deal brokered by Henry Clay and Stephen Douglas that many historians believe postponed the Civil War for a decade.", "answer": "<b> Compromise of 1850</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A military dictator of this country was famed for making civil servants who were late to work do squat-jumps; that leader won an election as the head of the All Progressives\u2019Congress with support from this country\u2019s (+) Hausa ethnic group. This country was once led by Goodluck Jonathan, who lost the aforementioned election after being criticized for his weak response to a terrorist group led by (*) </b> Abubakar Shekau. For ten points, name this African country currently led by Muhammadu Buhari from the city of Abuja, the home country of Boko Haram.", "answer": "Federal Republic of<b> Nigeria</b> Page 10", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>A leader of this country signed the Osimo Treaty with Yugoslavia before joining a \u201cHistoric Compromise\u201d with his country\u2019s communist party. NATO commander James Dozier was kidnapped in, and rescued from, this country. In 1980, during this</b> <b>country\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Years of Lead [led], the NAR terrorist group killed 85 people in a</b> <b>Years of Lead [led], the NAR terrorist group killed 85 people in a</b> <b>bombing of Central Station in this country\u2019s city of (*)</b> <b>bombing of Central Station in this country\u2019s city of (*)</b> Bologna; that attack came two years after the Red Brigades\u2019 Mario Moretti killed Prime Minister Aldo Moro. For ten points, name this country where the Red Brigades carried out numerous assassinations in Rome.", "answer": "<b> Italy </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}